James Fish

design strategist & facilitator

+49 176 420 64 65 8 james.fish@gmail.com www.james.fish

Designer, facilitator, and music geek with 10+ years of experience helping organizations understand the needs of the people they serve, create better products and services, and build stronger design cultures along the way.

Skills 🔑

- Discovery
- Workshop conceptualization & facilitation
- Teambuilding
- Qualitative & quantitative research strategy
- Interviewing, contextual inquiry
- Task analysis, journey mapping
- Visual facilitation & storytelling
- Participatory & co-design methods
- Speculative design & strategic foresight
- Paper & digital prototyping
- Feature roadmapping
- Usability testing
- Market research & analysis
- Miro, Figma, Adobe XD, Sketch
- MS Office and Google Suite
- Adobe Creative Suite
- Jira, Confluence
 English (native)
 German C1
 Italian C1

Education 🕏

HPI d.School / Certificate, Basic and Advanced Tracks

2012 - 2013, Potsdam, Germany Learned human-centric design methods on projects with partner organizations.

Harvard University / A.B., Sociology (Economics minor)

2006 - 2010, Cambridge, MA, USA Qualitative/quantitative methods: race and identity, leadership and organizations, healthcare, social entrepreneurship

Professional Experience

Design Strategy Consultant (Freelance)

2017 - present

- Led a 6-month project to redesign a multi-user data analytics tool
 for intensive care unit clinical teams, identify product and service
 design issues, and create a mobile UX concept. Conducted
 dozens of user interviews, facilitated design thinking and
 speculative design workshops, prototyped and prioritized
 features alongside product team and senior leadership.
 ETIOMETRY, INC
- Organized and facilitated a 5-day Google Ventures Design Sprint for a construction tools company. Coached a team of 9 (including senior executives) in design thinking methods. Assessed strategic goals and market needs, prototyped an app concept, recruited and tested with 5 participants. Their experience led them to continue development of the app and hire a full-time innovation manager. CALCULATED INDUSTRIES
- Created and tested a 'masterclass' series of design thinking workshops for HR professionals alongside an HR consulting agency. Facilitated numerous internal vision, mission, and strategy alignment workshops. LISANTIX GMBH

Colab Cooperative / Senior Design Strategist



2019 - present

Colab is a decentralized, transnational tech worker cooperative that serves mission-driven organizations through agile, cooperative digital co-design.

- Led redesign of a web+mobile logistics tool that helps food rescues more efficiently coordinate donations, communicate with volunteers, and see where needs arise across communities. Needfinding, journey mapping, participatory co-design facilitation, wireframing, testing, iteration, feature prioritization, and feedback. The interactive prototype tested well with project partners and volunteers and is currently in development. THE FOOD RESCUE ALLIANCE
- Designed and prototyped an open-source web tool for climate researchers to model carbon emissions and cost projections for various technologies. PROJECT DRAWDOWN
- Designed and prototyped a novel digital media website concept for the relaunch of a social change "storytelling" organization for artists and activists of color. Research, synthesis, conceptualization, wireframing, prototyping features and layout. THE CENTER FOR CULTURAL POWER

James Fish

design strategist & facilitator

+49 176 420 64 65 8 james.fish@gmail.com www.james.fish

Interests ♥

- Electronic music production, sound design, live performance, DJing
- Music technology: human-computer interfaces, hardware & software instrument design
- Interactive & immersive event production
- Dance (modern, hip hop, flow arts)

Elsewhere ☑

Design strategy portfolio
LinkedIn
Soundcloud
Event production portfolio

HPI d.School & HPIAcademy / Coach





- Guided student teams in design thinking methods and collaboration dynamics on 12-week projects from launch to project partner handover, including two rounds of needfinding, prototyping, and design iteration. Coached teams of professionals in 3-5 day "Intro to Design Thinking" workshops. Mentored participants, gave feedback throughout their projects.
- Created and customized workshops and activities.

Proteus Digital Health / UX Researcher



2014 - 2017, Redwood City, CA, USA

Responsibilities spanned foundational and generative design research, including needfinding, concept testing, design thinking, and product strategy, synthesizing insights into recommendations for our product team.

- Designed and ran a study evaluating Proteus web portal in clinical workflow context
 - Conducted 14 interviews at 3 customer sites with nurses, doctors, patients, and caregivers, and 11 interviews with naive users in our target market, to evaluate workflows and test feature concepts
 - Synthesized hundreds of insights into 160 user stories, themes, and a feature roadmap
- Co-created a framework for patient health engagement based on peer-reviewed behavioral science
 - Reviewed primary and secondary literature and meta-analyses on behavior change, design, and health
 - Led team in design thinking workshops to ideate features for patient engagement and behavior change
 - Designed an in-app notifications system to motivate users to adopt healthier behaviors
- Coordinated setup at a new customer site, and ran a real-time, longitudinal service design study over 3 months
 - Developed, programmed, and delivered user feedback surveys through Qualtrics
 - Assisted with evaluative research and usability studies